Guide to the Willbur Fisk Papers, 1812 - 1883
Willbur Fisk Papers, 1812 - 1883
Special Collections & Archives, Wesleyan University
Fisk, Willbur.
1000-91
6.5
13
Willbur Fisk (1792-1839) was a Methodist minister and the first president of Wesleyan University.
The Willbur Fisk Papers consist of two large series, Correspondence and Papers. The Papers feature items related to Wesleyan University, including his acquisition of scientific equipment. They also contain Fisk's own writings and sermons, on topics ranging from abolitionism to Methodist issues. A subset of the Papers are items written by or belonging to Ruth Peck Fisk, the wife of Willbur Fisk.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
No restrictions. Some material is fragile and must be handled with care.
Acquisitions Information
Materials collected by the college library in the 19th century. Contact Special Collections & Archives Staff for more information, available in the Willbur Fisk collections file.
Biographical Note
Willbur Fisk, Wesleyan’s first president, was born on 31 August 1792 and grew up in Brattleboro, Vermont. Although his mother feared that godlessness and sin in schools and colleges would make Fisk too worldly and strangle the spiritual life, Fisk graduated from Brown University in 1815, after also attending Peacham Academy and the University of Vermont. Surprisingly, given his future role at Wesleyan, Fisk was not initially drawn to the Methodist ministry following school. In fact, he struggled with his spiritual purpose at that time, working in law and as a tutor. However, a revelation during a bout of illness brought him to the ministry in 1818, and he devoted the rest of his life to his work as a Methodist. In 1825, Fisk was appointed principal of Wesleyan Academy in Wilbraham, Massachusetts, a preparatory school from which many Wesleyan University students were to be drawn.
Fisk was active within the Methodist Church on a number of issues, including the importance of education, temperance, missionary work, and his opposition to abolitionist movements.
When the decision to found a university in Middletown, Connecticut was made, Fisk was tapped for the role of first president. In his inaugural speech in 1831, he outlined his vision for the university, encapsulated by the statement that Education should be directed in reference to two objects—the good of the individual educated and the good of the world. Fisk was deeply involved in the administrative and curricular decisions of Wesleyan, and raised funds for the new college. He traveled to Europe to study educational institutions and collect scientific equipment in 1835-1836, and also took that time as a break from the stresses of the presidency. Suffering from ill-health his entire life, Fisk finally succumbed on 22 February 1839 while still serving as president.
Willbur Fisk married Ruth Peck on 9 June 1823, and they had one adopted daughter, Martha.
Collection Overview
The Willbur Fisk Papers consist of two large series. The first, Correspondence, is arranged into two groups: letters to Willbur Fisk, and letters from Willbur Fisk. Both groups are arranged alphabetically. There are links in the finding aid to complete inventories of the letters. The letters from Willbur Fisk have both alphabetical and chronological inventories, although the letters are physically arranged in alphabetical order.
The second series, Papers, are items written or collected by Willbur Fisk and his wife Ruth Peck Fisk. These include number of papers related to Wesleyan University and its founding, such as correspondence and other materials about faculty and students, scientific equipment for the univeristy, and financial issues. Many of Fisk's own writings can also be found in this series, on topics ranging from abolitionism to Methodist issues. A number of Fisk's early schoolwork, featuring reports and poems, is listed under Compositions. Addresses and sermons written and delivered by Fisk can also be found in the Papers series.
A subset of the Papers are items written by or belonging to Ruth Peck Fisk. These primarily consist of writings about her husband, and letters to Mrs. Fisk after her husband's death. There are also a few printed items belonging to Mrs. Fisk in this series.
Online Catalog Headings
These and related materials may be found under the following headings in online catalogs.
Fisk, Wilbur, 1792-1839.; Fisk, Ruth Peck.; Wesleyan University (Middletown, Conn.)--Faculty.; Wesleyan University (Middletown, Conn.)--Finance.; Wesleyan University (Middletown, Conn.)--History--19th century.; Wesleyan University (Middletown, Conn.)--Presidents.; Wesleyan University (Middletown, Conn.)--Students.; Methodist Episcopal Church--Clergy.; Methodist Episcopal Church--New England--History.; Methodist Episcopal Church--History--19th century.; African Americans--Colonization.; Slavery and the church--Methodist Episcopal Church.; Scientific apparatus and instruments--History--19th century.
Willbur Fisk vertical files, Vertical (Subject) Files, Special Collections & Archives, Wesleyan University
Nineteenth Century Administrative Records, Special Collections & Archives, Wesleyan University
Detailed Description of the Collection
- Series 1. Correspondence
  - Letters to Willbur Fisk
    For a complete alphabetical list of correspondents to Willbur Fisk, including date ranges and numbers of letters, visit http://www.wesleyan.edu/libr/schome/FAs/fi1000-91a.html
    - A-B (Box 1)
    - C-Fisk (Box 2)
    - Fitch-I (Box 3)
    - J-Merrill (Box 4)
    - Merritt-Rood (Box 5)
    - Round-Z (Box 6)
  - Letters from Willbur Fisk
    For a complete alphabetical list of the recipients of letters from Willbur Fisk, including date ranges and numbers of letters, visit http://www.wesleyan.edu/libr/schome/FAs/fi1000-91b.html. For a complete chronological list of the letters from Willbur Fisk, visit http://www.wesleyan.edu/libr/schome/FAs/fi1000-91c.html.
    - 1812-7 September 1835 (Box 7)
    - 30 September 1835-24 January 1839 (Box 8)
- Series 2. Papers
  - Autobiography and Daybook, 1819 (Box 9)
    Parentage, early life, story of his salvation.
  - Papers pertaining to Wesleyan University
    - Report of the committee (Laban Clark, chairman; Willbur Fisk, Secretary) appointed by the New York & New England Annual Conferences to take into consideration the establishment of a college or University.... New Haven, 3 December 1829
      The committee mentions offers from Bridgeport, Wilbraham, and Middletown, and recommends Middletown for the site of the new institution to be established and the report also outlines plans for the financing and administration of the college. Letter to Dear Brother (Laban Clark?) appended at end, signed W. Fisk. All in the handwriting of Willbur Fisk.
    - Report of the Introductory School, signed by W. Fisk, 14 May 1831
    - Financial papers concerning purchase of the Columbian Orrery, 29 June 1837
    - Financial papers about apparatus purchased from Pro. J. M. Smith, undated
      Professor John Mott Smith died in December 1832.
    - A list of Apparatus, with prices, undated
    - List of chemicals purchased from Smith & Hodgson (Philadelphia) with prices, 30 August 1832
    - Memorandum in handwriting of Pres. Willbur Fisk concerning part-time appointment of Daniel H. Chase (class of 1933) as assistant in Mathematics and Ancient Languages, 26 March 1834
    - Unfinished address for Commencement, 1833
    - Suggestions of the president on a resident agency, about 1834-1835
      Proposals of substitute arrangements for the present in place of appointment of a special resident agent.
    - Reports to the Prudential Committee, 1834-1835
      Papers in the handwriting of Willbur Fisk having to do with nominations to the professorship of Moral and Intellectual Philosophy: Nathan Bangs, Joseph Holdich, Henry B. Bascom.
    - Communication from the professors, 1835
      Signed by A. W. Smith (and in his handwriting), D. D. Whedon, and J. F. Huber, concerning the responsibility and authority of the Faculty in nominating candidates for appointment to the Faculty.
    - Inventory of Stock & Tools in Carpenter Shop, May 1835
    - Stores in Wesleyan University, undated
    - Letter from Joseph Toby (Middletown) to Mr. Franklin Delano (New York City), 10 August 1835
      Requests Mr. Delano to arrange passage on the ship Roscoe for President and Mrs. Fisk, on favorable terms. Handwritten. The Fisks later sailed on the Roscoe, September 1835, bound for Liverpool.
    - Letter from John Forsyth, U. S. Secretary of State, to Noah A. Phelps, 20 July 1835
      Concerns W. Fisk's passport. Copy.
    - Certificate of Arrival at Port of London, 29 June 1836
      Contains some vital statistics about W. Fisk.
    - Communication concerning the case of Benjamin W. Britt (non-graduate, class of 1840), 1837
    - Financial Committee Report, April 1835
      Signed by W. Fisk, J. L. Smith, and H. Bangs.
    - Expenses at the Different Colleges, undated
    - Merit List, Winter Term, 1834-1835
      Handwriting of W. Fisk.
    - List of persons to receive 1837-1838 catalogues, October 1837
    - List of money received by Dr. Fisk at the New England Conference for Subscriptions, etc...., 1838
    - Proposals to Rev. John Seys on the Exchange of housees, agreed to by him, 8 October 1838
    - List of students who are to room in the (Seth) Camp house (with charges for rent, this in handwriting of J. F. Huber), 8 October 1838
      With charges for rent, this in handwriting of J. F. Huber.
    - Faculty recommendation that Rev. William M. Willett be appointed Teacher of Hebrew, January 1838
    - Rules for the Boarding Hall, spring term, 1838
    - Handwritten draft of a memorial addressed to the Connecticut Legislature, 1837
      Petitions, in the name of the president & professors of the Wesleyan University that the existing law in relation to public amusements be preserved whole and entire. Handwriting of W. Fisk.
  - Annual reports as President of Wesleyan University, 1833, 1834, 1837, 1838
  - Miscellaneous papers (non-Wesleyan), circa 1800-1839
    These include correspondence, writings on missionary work and Methodism, poetry, travel souvenirs, and administrative documents.
  - Bills for equipment purchased in Europe, 1835-1836
    Includes bills for scientific and astronomical equipment.
  - Financial appeals (Wesleyan University)
    - Handwritten draft of an appeal to the Connecticut State Legislature for financial aid, 1834
    - Draft of a financial appeal to the Connecticut State Legislature, circa 1835-1836
      In handwriting of W. Fisk. Fragile condition.
  - Financial Papers, Wesleyan University
    - 1829-1830
    - 1831-1832
    - Financial statements, first term 1831-1832, winter term 1836-1837, spring term 1837
    - Papers concerning the cost and financing of the President's House, 1837-1838
    - Financial memoranda addressed to Prof. Jacob F. Huber, 1838
    - Financial statements concerning the Boarding Hall, 1834-1837
    - Various financial papers, 1833-1838
    - Handwritten drafts of subscription scholarship forms
      Not in W. Fisk's handwriting.
  - Letters concerning Willbur Fisk
    - Letters to Joseph Holdich from various people about Willbur Fisk
      Joseph Holdich was the author of The Life of Willbur Fisk, D.D. (New York: Harper, 1842)
    - Letter regarding Willbur Fisk's choice of Brown University over Middlebury, 1840
      At Middlebury, Fisk was apparently insulted by its President Davis. He had to choose a new school after the War of 1812 closed Burlington University in Vermont.
    - Letters of introduction to various Englishmen, 1835
      Sent from Elliott Cresson, Secretary of the Colonization Society, Philadelphia, Edward Everett, and others.
    - Letters regarding students
      Most are not to or from Willbur Fisk.
    - Letters concerning Willbur Fisk, 1841, 1853
  - Bills and accounts of Wesleyan Academy, Wilbraham, Massachusetts, circa 1830
  - Financial papers - personal
  - Funeral arrangements and memorials, 1839
  - Will (copy) and provisions for Mrs. Ruth Fisk and adopted daughter Martha, 1839
  - Editorial correspondence
    - 1827-1839
      Handwritten.
    - Regarding Wesleyan
      - Description of Wesleyan's offerings, Zion's Herald, September 1833
      - Dr. T. Sewall's An Examination of Phrenology in 2 parts, reviewed, Christian Advocate and Journal, April 1837
      - Appeal to State for financial aid, Middletown Sentinel, October 1838
      - Death of A. C. Bangs, The Christian Advocate and Journal, 1838
    - Abolitionism
      - Part of a (long) letter on Abolitionism Commenced in 1835 but never finished, 1835
        Note and letter in handwriting of Willbur Fisk. Addressed to Brother Kingsbury.
      - Letter from Colonization Society of the City of New York to Wesleyan University: an appeal for contributions, 1832
      - Clippings of printed editorials by Fisk
      - Abolition statement to Zion's Herald by Brothers Palmer and Merritt, September 1837
    - Church affairs clippings, 1835-1838
    - Missions clippings and manuscripts, 1824-1839
    - Temperance, 1827-1834
      Includes address on temperance, 1832. Printed in North Star, Danville, Vermont, 17 April 1832
    - Theology clippings, 1826-1834
  - Lectures on philosophy and theology
    23 lectures, handwritten. Typed transcripts also available.
  - Church affairs, 1827-1828
  - Compositions
    - A composition concerning war, 11 September 1812
    - Willbur Fisk's Oration, 11 November 1812
    - The Fallacy of Human Happiness, 1 September [1812]
    - Happiness, 21 October 1812
    - The battle at Queenstown, 28 October 1812
    - The Lady of my Choice, 30 September 1812
    - Precedent, 5 August 1812
    - The ungrateful child, 7 October 1812
    - Remarks on the Life of Franklin: Priorities and principles worthy of imitation, January 1813
    - A moral chatechism: The Modern Fine Lady, 7 April 1813
    - Composition on Honor, 14 April 1813
    - Vermont: A Poem, 1813
    - The Happiness of Homes or The pleasures of Home, 19 May 1813
    - Mortality: A Paraphrase, 17 June 1814
    - Revolutions of time: 'Time rolls its ceaseless course,' 30 June 1814
    - Composition on Duplicity, 22 July 1814
    - Town and Country; Or, Which is best? 16 July 1814
    - Nature and Art Compared, undated
    - Willbur Fisk's Composition, 14 October 1814
    - Willbur Fisk's Composition, 20 August 1814
    - Hope, 28 April 1813
    - Homo/De Homine, 11 November 1814
    - The Trifler, No. II, 1814
    - On Death, undated
    - On Distinction, undated
    - "He hath a daily bauty in his life that makes me ugly,' 10 March 1815
    - The Annunciation, 8 September 1824
    - Loquaicity, undated
    - On Government, undated
      2 separate essays.
    - Passage of Time/Commencement Piece, undated
    - Tobacco, undated
    - Louisiana #1, undated
    - Louisiana #2, undated
    - On Reading, undated
    - Manuscript copies of poems by Willbur Fisk, copied by Ruth Peck Fisk, his wife
  - Addresses
    Manuscript and newspaper accounts
    - Address at Baltimore on behalf of superannuated ministers, widows, and orphans, 20 March 1838
      Two copies, one in Fisk's handwriting.
    - Address delivered at Wilbraham on leaving that School, 1831?
    - Address before the American Bible Society, May 1835
    - Addresses in Middletown
      - 25 February 1834
      - 4 July 1834
      - 24 February 1835
      - 27 February 1838
    - Dr. Fisk's Address to the members of the Methodist Episcopal Church on the Subject of Temperance, 1832
      2 published copies, plus newspaper account.
    - Dr. W. Fisk's Address at the Anniversary of the New York City Temperance Society, circa 1833
    - Sketches for a speech, undated
    - Missionary Spirit, undated
    - Untitled speech, undated
    - Address to the New York Conference, undated
  - Papers concerning the trial of Elias Marble, 1831-1835
  - The Sunderland controversy, 1838
  - License to preach, Lyndon, Vermont, March 1818 (Box 11)
  - Principal heads of discourses, delivered on various subjects, 7 July 1819
    One volume.
  - Sermons
    Over four hundred handwritten sermons.
  - Ruth Peck Fisk (Mrs. Willbur Fisk)
    - Death of Willbur Fisk (Box 12)
      - Willbur Fisk: Poem in the handwriting of Ruth Peck Fisk (Mrs. Willbur Fisk)
      - Letter from Ruth Peck Fisk to the parents of Willbur Fisk, concerning the latter's death, 28 March 1839
    - Letters from Mrs. Fisk
      - Unaddressed, unsigned letter (possibly a copy by Mrs. Fisk) complaining of Rev. Heman Bangs' non-performance as Agent (for Wesleyan University)
      - To Mr. and Mrs. J. Toby, undated
        2 different letters.
      - Diary jottings by Ruth Peck Fisk (Mrs. W. F.) - on the sailing ship Roscoe, returning from Europe, November 1836
        Pressed flowers, etc. from travels and letter mentioning tickets to Vatican, 1836.
      - To her mother from Paris, 5 November 1836
      - Various letters, circa 1839-1844
      - Two copies of a letter of 13 May 1839 from Mrs. Fisk to Rev. Dr. Bangs (probably Nathan Bangs), dwelling upon her late husband's final illness, his exhausting exertions, his final words, etc.
        Copy #2 contains some final portions not contained in Copy #1.
    - Notes concerning the life of her husband, President Willbur Fisk
      Draft outline of a biography?
    - Notes for Mr. Holdich by Ruth P. Fisk on life of and anecdotes concerning Willbur Fisk
      See Joseph Holdich's The Life of Willbur Fisk, D.D.: New York, 1842
    - 2 copies of page 9 of the 10 October 1884 College Argus regarding the death of Ruth Peck Fisk
    - Comments by R. Fisk on Mr. Holdich's book (Biography of Willbur Fisk, 1842)
    - Letters to Mrs. Fisk from members of her family and friends, 1823-1858
      - From her mother Lydia Peck, 1825-1832
        7 letters. Several mentions of adopted daughter Martha.
      - From members of the Peck family, 1840-1858
        2 letters.
      - From members of the Peck family, 1842-1844
        4 letters.
      - From Mrs. Mary Allton, 1843-1844
        10 letters. Mention of Martha's death in 1844.
      - From Miss Mary Goodwin, 1823
      - From Miss Penelope Lippett, 1828-1833
        5 letters.
      - From Mrs. Susan B. Thomas, 1840-1843
    - Financial accounts, receipts, etc., 1839-1874
    - Miscellaneous items
      - Poems by Ruth Peck Fisk
        3 items.
      - Calling cards
      - 1828 booklet, Canary Bird Fancier
      - Sunday School class book, R. Fisk, teacher
      - Greeting Cards
      - Notebook with last jottings, 1879
      - Letters to Mrs. Peck (Ruth Peck Fisk's mother) regarding payment of collected debt, 10 August 1835
        2 items.
      - Rules to be Observed in Parsing
      - Shell pattern knitting
    - Letters to Mrs. Fisk from various people, many regarding Dr. Fisk's death
      - Adams, S. E., 1839
      - Alder, Catherine, 1839
      - Alder, R., 1839-1840
      - Allen, J. R., 1840
      - Allen, R. C., undated
      - Andrew, J. F., 1872-1882
      - Arnold, Joseph and others, 1839
      - Baker, Osmon C., 1939
      - Balmer, Agnes, 1836
      - Bangs, N., 1839
      - Brewer, Susan, 1828
      - Burrass, John W., 1839
      - Caldwell, M., 1839
      - Chamberlain, Elizabeth, 1825
      - Chandler, S. M., 1881
      - Clopton, D. and others, 1839
      - Cummings, D. S., 1878
      - Dwight, M., 1845
      - Emory, Robert, 1847
      - Frothingham, Sally, undated
      - Goodwin, A. C., 1831
      - Goodwin, Martha, 1830
      - Gordon, W., 1845
      - Hall, Fanny W., 1839
      - Hallenbeck, Valentine, 1882
      - Hand, S. S., 1842
      - Harrington, Eliza C., 1882
      - Hoffart, J. P., 1883
      - Holdich, L. H., 1835
      - Huber, Jacob F., 1841
      - Johnston, Anna L., 1877
      - Johnston, John, 1877
      - Knowlton, Marcia, 1839
      - Lane, Charles L., 1874-1875
      - Lane, J. J., 1844
      - Larrabee, Harriet, 1839
      - Mattocks, E., 1841-1842
      - Mead, H., 1821
      - Miner, W. A., 1876-1883
      - Michell, H. G., 1870-1879
      - Otheman, B. Hall, 1839
      - Paine, Lydia, undated
      - Patten, David, 1839
      - Pevin, H., 1839
      - Porter, Lansing, undated
      - Price, J., 1839
      - Raynor, E., 1839-1840
      - Reid, M. Morrison, 1840
      - Richardson, C., 1839
      - Richardson, Martha, 1840
      - Roberts, Joanna, 1843
      - Robins, Priscilla, 1828
      - Sewell, Thomas, 1839
      - Smith, N., 1844
      - Snow, A. B. and others, 1839
      - Staples, M. R., 1844
      - Stiles, S. M., undated
      - Stows, Samuel F., 1839
      - Tabor, M., 1836
      - Taylor, Maria F., 1844
      - Toby, Joseph, 1840
      - Tobey, Joseph and Eliza, 1830
      - True, C. K., 1860
      - Webb, Isaac, 1841
      - Webb, S. I., 1846
      - Whedon, D. D., 1840
      - Whitman, I., 1845
      - Whittelsey, H., 1838-1843
      - Willett, E., 1845
      - Willett, William M., 1840
      - Winde, George Willis, 1842
      - Wood, E. R., 1827
      - Woodruff, G. W. and E. W., 1862
    - Piece of wedding shawl, 9 June 1828
    - Manuscript verse, mostly about Willbur Fisk, by Ruth Peck Fisk, circa 1839 (Box 13)
    - Engraved sheet of music entitled Fisk, words by Mrs. Dr. Fisk, music by C. S. H.
      5 copies.
    - Scrapbook of clippings and extracts on her husband's death
    - List of subscribers to the $2,000 fund for Ruth Peck Fisk after Willbur Fisk's death
    - Commonplace book: Extracts and Sentiments
    - Ruth Peck Fisk's copy of Hannah More's Search After Happiness, 1773. Lacks title page.
    - Ruth Peck Fisk's copy of Willbur Fisk's Travels in Europe, 4th edition, 1838, bound for her
    - 2 copies of Chauncey Bascom's Guide to Chirography in a Series of Writing Books... Middletown: Published and Sold by E. Hunt, 1832. Filled out by Martha Fisk in 1835.